<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Marohn Group</title><link href="http://johnmarohn.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://johnmarohn.github.io/feeds/news.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://johnmarohn.github.io/</id><updated>2016-05-12T15:32:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Outreach activities at Caroline Elementary School</title><link href="http://johnmarohn.github.io/MarohnGroup-20160512-153241--Outreach-activities-at-Caroline-Elementary-School.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-05-12T15:32:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Hoang Long Nguyen (hn269@cornell.edu)</name></author><id>tag:johnmarohn.github.io,2016-05-12:MarohnGroup-20160512-153241--Outreach-activities-at-Caroline-Elementary-School.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On May 4th, 2016, graduate students from the Marohn laboratory brought liquid nitrogen to Caroline Elementary School for various scientific activities and demonstrations. The goal of this outreach was to help fifth graders understand the physical properties of liquid nitrogen (liquid phase, cold -321 &lt;span class="formula"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;○&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; F), and phase changes. Our activities&amp;nbsp;included&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We deflated air balloons with liquid nitrogen, and stuffed many of them into a small container. Then, we took the balloons out one by one and let them deflate at room temperature and asked the students to explain what they saw. We then re-froze one of the balloons to show that the gases inside the balloon actually&amp;nbsp;liquified.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We froze a few pennies in liquid nitrogen &amp;#8212; some old and some new.  We asked the students what they expected to see when the coins were frozen.  We took the pennies out and smashed them with a hammer to demonstrate that metal became brittle when cold. The new pennies shattered easily while the older one only bent a little.  We asked the students to deduce something about the pennies from what they saw.  We explained that the different behaviors resulted from differences in the material composition of the pennies &amp;#8212; the newer coins (after 1982) were made of zinc and coated with a thin layer of copper while the older coins were made entirely of&amp;nbsp;copper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In another activity, we froze a banana in liquid nitrogen and tried to use it to smash a pile of frozen coins. The banana was shattered while the coins remained intact. We explained that the frozen banana was more fragile because of its high water and sugar&amp;nbsp;content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In our last activity, we let the students freeze a few marshmallows in liquid nitrogen.  We then let them eat this frozen treat!  It did not hurt; rather, they found it tasty and cold like ice-cream. Some students were able to breathe out foggy smoke through their nose. Very&amp;nbsp;cool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These activities were repeated for two classes of fifth graders and they all enjoyed it. Some students demonstrated quite a bit of prior knowledge (&amp;#8216;I saw it in a Youtube video before&amp;#8217;) and a great affinity for science through their clear explanations and keen observations.  In an unofficial vote, our activities were found to be the coolest the students had experienced yet in their fifth grade science&amp;nbsp;class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="an image" src="images/20160504_Caroline_pic1.JPG" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Fig 1: Balloons taken out of liquid nitrogen re-inflate by&amp;nbsp;themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="an image" src="images/20160504_Caroline_pic2.JPG" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Fig 2: Marshmallows frozen with liquid&amp;nbsp;nitrogen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="an image" src="images/20160504_Caroline_pic3.JPG" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Fig 3: Fifth-graders watching the liquid nitrogen&amp;nbsp;demonstration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Marohn Group at Cornell Expanding Your Horizons (EYH)</title><link href="http://johnmarohn.github.io/MarohnGroup-20160505-145552--Marohn-Group-at-Cornell-Expanding-Your-Horizon-(EYH).html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-05-05T14:55:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Hoang Long Nguyen (hn269@cornell.edu)</name></author><id>tag:johnmarohn.github.io,2016-05-05:MarohnGroup-20160505-145552--Marohn-Group-at-Cornell-Expanding-Your-Horizon-(EYH).html</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;On April 30, 2016, Marohn Group graduate students led two separate workshops at the annual &lt;em&gt;Expanding Your Horizons Conference&lt;/em&gt; at Cornell University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this day-long conference was to introduce middle-school-aged girls to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; fields (Science, Techonology, Engineering and Mathematics) through various demonstrations, discussions, and hands-on experiences. Members of our laboratory designed two different, exciting workshops.  One workshop, “Juice from Juice: Berry Solar Cell”, was designed for 7th and 8th graders.  This workshop provided an introduction to the design and construction of a simple organic solar cell. The other workshop, “Turning on the Light”, was designed for 9th graders who have more experience thinking about electricity, work, and magnetism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to leading workshops, many Marohn-laboratory members held leadership positions within the &lt;em&gt;Expanding Your Horizons&lt;/em&gt; organization, helping to ensure that the April 30th event ran well.  We are happy to report that after months of preparation the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYH&lt;/span&gt; conference went off smoothly and successfully!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="juice-from-juice-berry-solar-cell"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id1"&gt;Juice from Juice - Berry Solar Cell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img alt="Juice from Juice" class="align-center" src="../images/Juice_from_Juice_201604.png"/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘Juice from Juice’ workshop where middle-school aged girls learn about organic solar cells and made their own berry-power cells. Upper Left: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ITO&lt;/span&gt;-slide is soaked in chosen berry juice; Upper Right: workshop leaders explaining the working concept and the simple construction of berry solar cells; Middle: Workshop leaders during lunch break; Lower Left: a workshop leader demonstrates the step-by-step construction of berry solar cell to the girls and parents; Lower Right: Girls taking note while building their solar cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="turning-on-the-light"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id2"&gt;Turning on the Light&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img alt="Turning on the Light" class="align-center" src="../images/Turning_Light_201604.png"/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘Turning on the Light’ workshop where girls are building their own wind electricity generators using simple tools and magnets. Above: The girls are winding copper wires around a plastic tube for magnet feedthrough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="outreach"></category><category term="EYH"></category></entry><entry><title>Photo Album</title><link href="http://johnmarohn.github.io/MarohnGroup-20160404-180802--Photo-Album.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-04-04T18:08:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Hoang Long Nguyen (hn269@cornell.edu)</name></author><id>tag:johnmarohn.github.io,2016-04-04:MarohnGroup-20160404-180802--Photo-Album.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;img alt="Marohn Group 2015 Holiday Party" class="align-center" src="../images/Group201512reduced.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;div class="center line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marohn Group Holiday Party in December 2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Left to right:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Back row:&lt;/strong&gt; Hoang, John Marohn, Patty, Michael, Ali, Aubrey, Christian, Corinne;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Front row:&lt;/strong&gt; Laura, Ryan, Louisa, John Smieska, Andrew, Beth&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;img alt="Marohn Group 2015 Summer Picnic" class="align-center" src="../images/Group201506.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;div class="center line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marohn Group Pinic in June 2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Left to right:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Back row:&lt;/strong&gt; Michael Boucher, Corinne Isaac, Sarah Nathan, John Marohn, Hoang Long Nguyen;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Front row:&lt;/strong&gt; Ali Tirmzi, Sherry Li, Jazmin, Beth Curley, Paméla Nasr, Ryan Dwyer&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;img alt="Marohn Group Spring 2015" class="align-center" src="../images/Group201505reduced.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;div class="center line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marohn Group in May 2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Left to right:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Back row:&lt;/strong&gt; Louisa Smieska, Ryan Dwyer, John Marohn, Michael Boucher;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Middle row:&lt;/strong&gt; Sarah Nathan, Beth Curley, Ali Tirmzi;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Front row:&lt;/strong&gt; Paméla Nasr, Hoang Long Nguyen, Corinne Isaac&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;img alt="Marohn Group 2014" class="align-center" src="../images/Group201404reduced.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;div class="center line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marohn Group in April 2014&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Left to right:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Back row:&lt;/strong&gt; Louisa Smieska, John Marohn, Jimmy O&amp;#8217;Dea, Ryan Dwyer;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Middle row:&lt;/strong&gt; Hoang Long Nguyen, Beth Curley, Corinne Isaac, Sherry Li;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Front row:&lt;/strong&gt; Sarah Nathan, Paméla Nasr, Christine Gleave&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;img alt="Marohn Group 2014" class="align-center" src="../images/Group201304reduced.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;div class="center line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marohn Group in April 2013&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Left to right:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Back row:&lt;/strong&gt; John Marohn, Alex Senko, Corinne Isaac;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second-to-back row:&lt;/strong&gt; Ryan Dwyer, Joseph Singh, Louisa Smieska;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second-to-front row:&lt;/strong&gt; Hoang Long Nguyen, Sarah Nathan, Lei Chen, Sam Young;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Front row:&lt;/strong&gt; Sherry Li, Christine Gleave, Paméla Nasr, Joni Longenecker, Jimmy O&amp;#8217;Dea&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="photo"></category></entry><entry><title>Welcome</title><link href="http://johnmarohn.github.io/MarohnGroup-20150703-174539--Welcome.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-03T17:45:00-04:00</updated><author><name>John A. Marohn (jam99@cornell.edu)</name></author><id>tag:johnmarohn.github.io,2015-07-03:MarohnGroup-20150703-174539--Welcome.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Marohn group&amp;#8217;s new&amp;nbsp;website!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>